All right. I'm Sam Agnew, Chair of the Health Committee.
You all know other members around the table. Very good to have you here.
Thank you for joining us, to discuss the report of the Ombudsman OIA timeliness
obligations at Health New Zealand. So, I'll just move straight into it.
We are in public session, and I'll open it up for questions. Ingrid Leary.
Thank you very much, Mr. Chair. Hello, officials.
I note that Radio New Zealand has mentioned that Health New Zealand is the most
complained about organization when it comes to compliance with the OIA, and there
were 92 complaints in the past six months.
I have done quite a few OIAs to you. In fact, I've done 92, and I
note that just under 20% of my requests were not answered within 20 days,
and about 10% of my requests, so that's 10 out of 92, required extensions.
And the longest one to come back was 147 days.
I note also that the two most controversial subjects, the 147-day one
was about mental health workforce plan that resulted in a story by TV3
about massaging of numbers by Jenna Lynch, and then there was Sega House, which had
63 days delay. So I just have a series of questions, if I may, regarding
what your policy is around seeking extensions, and what
do you think is an acceptable percentage of OIA requests to make that to?
Look, I'll start to speak to that. My name's Catherine Delor.
I'm the Chief Communications and Government Services Officer for Health New
Zealand, and I'm also joined online today by Richard May,
who is the National Director of the business unit that oversees my area.
I think to answer to your question,
what is an acceptable percentage, I would like to think that we would actually
manage that down to
a very minimal amount,
and so we move our OIAs through as quickly as we can.
We are absolutely aware of our obligations under the Official Information Act.
I would also acknowledge the Ombudsman's report.
I think some of the stuff that has been reported about us struggling to meet some
of those obligations. But we have done a bit of a reset at Health New
Zealand, and we've got quite a focus on this area as one of the priorities for
improvement over the next period.
So I would like to think that we would get to 100% timeliness, but we're on a bit
of a journey for that.
Just supplementary, Mr. Chair. Thank you.
Do you
keep a schedule of the ones where you've asked for extensions?
I know that that came up with Pharmac.
Is that something you've done as a protocol now?
We do have regular tracking and records of extensions, and we've
also gone back with very clear direction about,
an extension is not something that is automatically granted.
There needs to be a really strong case for it.
For example, where it might be one that is particularly complex data.
You might understand we have the 20 district health boards and other entities.
We still have information sitting in different systems.
So it is not to be a default for Health New Zealand.
It is where we can see a case where it might take us longer to do that.
So just for clarity, there is a separate schedule that belongs to extensions where
those particular Official Information Act documents, so that if somebody sought
that data, you would have a schedule that would say, "These are all the OIAs where
extensions have been."
We've certainly got
records of that.
As a discrete record which was recommended to Pharmac?
I'm just wanting to see if your protocols are-
The OIA team does record those extensions.
I would have to say that we do not have the best tracking tool either as one
organization, and we're currently in the process of procuring a new workflow tool
that will give us real time information on where an OIA is sitting, where it is
stuck. So not only we as the team managing that for the organization have that
visibility, but also, so the business can be really held to
account for where they're at in that process.
I'm not sure if Richard wants to add anything further to that.
I think that's fine. I've got some questions around proactive releases, if I may.
What is your policy regarding proactive releases, and what's an acceptable
timeframe to proactively release documents?
We do have a policy around proactive release, and we are trying to get
more into that practice than we have been.
I would acknowledge that we have not achieved what we should in this area, but it
is a focus for the coming period. We, as you might be aware,
have gone through some reorganization in the organization, and as part of that
for government services, we are looking at
ways in which we can enhance our reporting.
So what is an acceptable timeframe for proactive release?
Oh, look, I would think as soon as we possibly can is acceptable.
Sorry, is that days, weeks, months?
Both. Yeah.
If I may. Yeah, because it is a line of questioning.
Talking about extensions, and I appreciate my colleagues put in 91.
Was it 91? 92?
92.
92. According to the report,
21.9% of OIAs was extended compared to
14% for other Crown agencies. But I appreciate Health New Zealand is a far
bigger, far more complex organization.
When you look at that 21.9%, have you got a breakdown to what has caused
those delays? Because I appreciate some of that data is going to be very complex
for you to get from, in effect, 20 different district health boards.
I think it largely has been an artifact effect of the maturity of Health New
Zealand and our systems and some of the inherited
systems and processes that we have had across the organization.
And I think also there have been different levels of understanding across our
workforce and those who we need to support the work in Health New Zealand and the
different areas of the organization about actually what good practice looks like,
and we have put additional effort and work into trying to lift OIA understanding
and capability. We use the online training tool that the Ombudsman has, as well as
doing some in-house sessions for people.
The figure that you refer to is again, something that we want to and need to
improve on.
I've met, along with the chief executive, their new ombudsman earlier this year,
and we have regular meetings with his office.
We've made that commitment, and we've explained some of the steps we're taking to
lift our performance.
So one more here, then I'll go back to Ingrid and to Florence as well.
Thank you.
Can you give the committee a feeling for how many OIA requests you'd receive a
week, and the breakdown, is that coming from journalists, the general public,
politicians?
All of those.
Patients, people within the sector.
Last year, for the calendar year 2024, we had
4,628 OIA requests. And at any one
time we may have 250 to-
Sure
... 300 live across the organization, and some of those requests are
extremely detailed. We do often have to take time to go back to the requester,
which we're committed to doing, and trying to refine it and understand what they're
looking for in those requests. But it is quite broad with health and the number of
interested parties, quite a broad
group of people who are sending in requests.
So you don't have a breakdown of- The origin of the request
I don't have a breakdown that I can provide you with today, but we could look to
try to do that.
All right. And good-
Thank you. Just a few more in this line of questioning, and then I'll be done.
Thank you for your answers, and I know that you didn't say what an acceptable time
period would be for proactive. You said as soon as possible.
Could you indicate is that days, weeks, or months?
Depending on what it is.
I would like to think that as we are working on a particular piece of work, that we
start to think about proactive release early on in that piece of work, so we are
ready to do a proactive release within weeks and days.
Thank you.
But that's just a business maturity thing we're working through.
And are you confident that the
information that is released is accurate and done when it is said to be proactively
released?
I'm confident that we have sought the right sign-off from those people who are
responsible for the information. We're not the subject matter experts for that.
We do rely on the knowledge and expertise within Health New Zealand.
Okay.
So we do take steps to get sign-off and verification of information.
And I'll come to sign-off in a second.
I just note that, for example, I put in a request for a mental health report,
February 17th, 2025. Weekly report was told under Section 18D it would be
proactively released. It still hasn't been done.
When we pointed out that it hadn't been done, your office turned it into an
official information act request that basically didn't provide the information.
So that's just an example. So let's come to the sign-offs.
Does the Minister's office need to approve any proactive release of documents?
We have a practice of sharing information with the Minister's office on a no
surprises basis.
So that's prior to it being released?
Usually there is a noting period for proactive releases.
And so what say, if any, does the Minister have in the approval of those proactive
releases and particularly the timing of them, given some of the delays that I've
just referred to?
I'm not sure if you want to touch on this, Richard.
And then just one final step after that, Mr. Chair.
Sorry. Is that we?
Yes.
We work with the Minister's office on a case-by-case basis and we
provide OIAs on a case-by-case under no surprises.
Okay. Well, I would just put it to you that it's very interesting to me that the
two most controversial topics that have been covered in Egan Hospital and Sega
House were the ones that had the biggest delays in terms of proactive releases and
also OIA responses. My final question is that last year, about a year ago, there
were 173 staff in the comms engagement team.
You've talked about restructure, and I get a sense of perhaps this is to do with
public service cuts. How many people do you have in the comms and engagement team
now?
We are partway through our
restructure of the communications and engagement team,
and we're still working through that.
Our final number will be closer to 100.
Okay. And just last question to Mr. May.
Can you rule out that the Minister has ever stopped you from releasing a document
or delayed a document that has been requested?
Has there ever been a direction or a request from the Minister's office to delay
the release of a document?
No, we work with the Minister's office as items come on a case-by-case basis.
No surprises. We work closely with the Minister's office.
Lawrence.
Thank you, Minister. I think these questions are really important, and I want to
just pick up on a supplementary question on the timeliness bit.
What is the process around,
I guess Te Whatu Ora, the Minister of Health, delaying or having
extension to an OIA request, but then knowing that they are going to
refuse the request under OIA anyway.
So the reason I also mention this is I've had a situation again with Te Whatu Ora
where I submitted an OIA request, and it was extended by four
months just for it to be refused.
So what is the process that goes through in terms of extension?
Do you check if you're going to be refusing this request anyway before you grant an
extension? Or are you not going to look at it for month and month and month, and
then when you finally after a month got around to looking at it, refuse it?
Look, I think an OIA that comes in is treated as such.
It is lodged in the system. We identify the responsible business
area. They do sometimes come to us and say, "We need to take more time on this."
I think that it is very clear that we can,
and we should, for a variety of reasons or a particular ground, refuse to
release information.
We would make that known as soon as possible.
We cannot always
be aware of the judgment that might be made in the business once they have taken a
closer look at a particular request. I acknowledge that four months is a long time.
We're just going to let members know that we're also looking at the report of the
Ombudsman around aged care monitoring.
If there are any questions that sort of report that.
Excellent. Thank you. And we've been thinking about the involvement of the
Minister's office, and there probably has been some political points trying to be
scored. In the Ombudsman report, there is a paragraph says, "I'm pleased to report
that I saw no evidence in sample files of inappropriate input from the Minister or
the Minister's office on departmental OIA reports," and the chief executive has a
similar sort of statement. Do you agree with the Ombudsman on that part of the
report?
Yes, I do.
Excellent. Thank you.
Lawrence.
A new question actually on the OCAT if people are finished with the OIA component.
Yeah. Go.
So the question in terms of OCAT aged care report, I guess one of the things that's
really telling is around the concern with regard to various
level of understanding facilities, medical professionals, and whānau had on the
required documentation for legal authority for residents.
And there was also concerns around sort of residents living in secure or
isolated environment.
Just want to check, I think broadly speaking, now that we have the report, what are
the steps that Te Whatu Ora or the Minister of Health is going to take to
meaningfully improve the conditions or build better understanding for the legal
authority requirements?
Excuse me. I'm Matt Cowlam, the Acting
National Director for Aging Well from Health New Zealand.
I'll respond initially and hand it over to my ministry colleagues.
Health New Zealand has developed national guidelines for aged
residential care facilities,
to help them to verify and record that each resident
has a legal valid basis for being placed into a secure service.
We have worked with the Ombudsman's office, the Aged Care Commissioner's office,
and the aged residential care sector to develop the guidelines.
They've been finalized. We're also
nearly finalized a checklist, which makes it very simple and clear for
the sector to ensure that people are lawfully
placed in aged residential care secure services.
That we're just waiting on the final feedback from the sector on that checklist
before we issue the two documents.
We expect that to be completed,
and issued in August.
Just a supplementary question. Thank you for that. That's really helpful.
Once it's operationalized within that guideline, are you able to tell us if there's
a built-in evaluation timeframe on when you're then going to go back and just
ensure that people do indeed follow the guidelines?
It probably sits more in the space of the ministry in terms of-
Certification and the audits around that.
Certainly, Health New Zealand,
we work very closely with the Ministry on audits, and that's one of the things that
we look at is, is the documentation for placement of people in secure care.
Rui, you may want to add further comment.
Thank you.
So my name is Rui Guaku. I'm from the Ministry of Health, and with me is Kirsten
Lacey. She's the manager of HealthCERT.
So HealthCERT is a regulatory team within the Ministry who is responsible for
the administration of Health and Disability Services Safety Act.
So under that act requirement, providers need to be certified
and they need to meet a certain standard.
And aged residential care providers are within the scope of this act.
HealthCERT, the relevant standard currently is Ngā
Parewa Health and Disabilities Services Standard that was published and put in
place in 2021, replacing previous standard.
Within the standard, Ngā Parewa, there are relevant criteria requiring
providers to ensure that they have the right documentation,
to ensure that people are in the right place and have the valid legal authority for
people to act on other people's behalf, and also includes requirement on
informed consent, and also that Ngā Parewa is also intended
to be interpreted consistent with other requirements within the health sector,
including Health and Disability Commissioner Code of Rights, which includes clearly
specific requirements about
informed consent, decision-making process, et cetera.
We also
administer our audit framework to ensure providers are checked and to ensure
they are meeting the requirement.
And part of the audit process for aged care sector,
is that we have incorporated the Health New Zealand contractual
requirement.
Well, it is relevant to the quality and safety of services delivery.
Thank you.
We're at time there. So, I want to say thank you to all of you from Health New
Zealand for coming in today and answering questions-
Mr. Chair-
... from the committee.
Given the short amount of time on this one, is it possible to do some post-hearing
questions?
We can consider that as a committee after this. Thank you very much.